VISHANTH HARI RAJ BALASUBRAMANIAN

+1 310 254 6562 vishanth.hari.raj.ucla@gmail.com www.linkedin.com/in/vishanthhariraj Github

SUMMARY

Committed and outcome-focused expert with a history of impact across innovation, Artificial Intelligence & Machine Learning, data analysis, data science, and product analysis and product management. Boasts a robust fusion of technical prowess, analytical acumen, and strategic insight. Over 3+ of leadership experience in analytics, software development in Fortune 100 tech enterprises.

IT Skills: R, Python, C/C++, JavaScript, TypeScript, HTML, Angular, Node.js (basic), SQL. OS- Windows, iOS, RHEL, Kali Linux, Linux **Tools:** R Studio, Git, Jira, Confluence, Tableau, Excel, Evolven, Splunk, MATLAB, Solidworks, Spark (basic), GitHub, Bitbucket. **Certifications:** Lean Six Sigma Green Belt CSSE-GB, Digital Transformation- BCG, Machine Learning in AWS- AWS.

EDUCATION

UCLA ANDERSON SCHOOL OF MANAGEMENT

Los Angeles, CA

Master of Science in Business Analytics (MSBA)

September 2023- December 2024

- **Courses**: Python, Optimization, SQL & Basic Data Management, Competitive Analytics, Business Fundamentals for Analytics, Machine Learning, Market Analytics, Statistics using R.
- Leadership: Vice President, Social Network and Marketing Student Government Body

NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY, TIRUCHIRAPALLI

Trichy, India

Bachelor of Technology in Industrial Engineering /Minor in Computer Science (GPA: 3.9/4.0)

July 2017 - June 2021

- Awards: Awarded Institute Merit Rank Award for securing the Top 3 ranks in the Department
- **Courses:** Project Management, Product Development Strategy, Big Data Analytics, Data Structure Algorithms, Computer Architecture, Supply Chain Management, DBMS etc.
- Leadership: Co-founder of Ignite Club, Student Council Member, Class Rep, Head of Events Team

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Citigroup (Citi Global Wealth - CGW)

Chennai, India

Tech Analyst 2 – Artificial Intelligence & Operations (Innovation Lab)

July 2022 - Sept 2023

- Managed AIOPS team of 4 software developers & a product manager; Led internal Innovation project on development of LLM, NLP & forecasting Machine Learning models & BOTs which saved +\$250K per year in Production Support Activities.
- Project Lead in establishing command center in Chennai & Lead Data Scientist on developing dashboards which pro-actively avoided more 50+ major incidents, reduced downtime by 10%, saved ~ \$1M across CGW application all overall the world.
- Innovation Manager in HNI / UHNI (High Net-worth Individuals) Division on enhancing the business model, technology innovation & strategy to offer better client services and experience in Citi wealth management application.
- Awarded Citi Gratitude Golden Award, Citi Copper Award, Bronze Award, Bravo Award and Citi-Client Obsession Award, and 10+ Applause award for best automation, Innovation works across CGW, Finalists in Citi Hackathon 2022

Tech Analyst 1 – Software Development (Personal Banking & Wealth Management Tech – PBWMT)

July 2021 - July 2022

- Designed new tech stack in innovation lab- Angular, Node.js, python, Al & ML algorithms to enhance automation app.
- Streamlined & Implemented new SDLC process (Agile) for internal Citibank applications, saved around 100+ person-hours.
- Integrated various monitoring tools (Splunk, Evolven, ServiceNow) through APIs to create a data lake for forecasting and analytics, which saved **\$100K** in monitoring and saved **300+** man-hours in monitoring and reporting.
- Developed full stack automation model using Machine Learning for proactive monitoring, incident forecasting, **SRE & SLA**, and impact analysis dashboards; were **reduced incidents by 13%** through this application compared to last year.

JOHN MOLSON SCHOOL OF BUSINESS, Concordia University, Canada

Montreal, Canada

MITACS Globalink Research Intern'20 – Software Development

April 2020 - July 2020

- Selected as MITACS Globalink Scholar GRI'20 (Indo Canadian Government Sponsored Research Internship) among a million participants from 14 countries.
- Developed a non-linear programming assortment model using various greedy algorithms in C++ to predict market demand and can **maximize profit by 6%** using the model, for Walmart Canada.

VEVOLVE (NIT TRICHY ALUMNI - STARTUP)

Bengaluru, India

Machine Learning Engineer Intern

May 2020 - Aug 2020

- Collaborated in a team of 3 for an R&D project and developed machine learning models in cybersecurity to evaluate the vulnerabilities of the PHP application, which generates **revenue share of \$30K** from this project.
- Worked on R& D product development closely with CEO and Co-founders and got mentored by them

Research Associate - Data Analytics

Developed a MATLAB model to analyze the <u>data (data processing and data visualization</u>) for engine variables and parameters,
 P-V graphs, exhaustion analysis, etc., to detected various abnormalities, for company-sponsored research on the development of a GDI (Gasoline Direct Injection) engine in a single cylinder under the guidance of Prof. A Ramesh; assisted in publishing a Research paper on it.

PROJECTS & PUBLICATIONS

Machine Learning Project: Collaborated with Hinduja Foundries to create an <u>image recognition-based machine learning model for automated defect detection</u> in manufacturing, achieving 90% accuracy and eliminating manual visual inspection, research paper is in process of publication.

ACHIEVEMENT

- Top 10 Finalists in Citi Hackathon (Idea Shuttle Innovation) in India- 2022
- Selected on ISB (Indian School of Business) Young Leadership Program'21
- Scored 750 in GMAT 99 Percentile with Quant 51 (full score).
- Institute Award NIT Trichy for securing the Top 3 ranks in the Department.
- Selected as MITACS Globalink Research Scholar'20 (Indo-Canadian Govt Joint Research Program)
- Secured All India Rank 349 in Graduate Aptitude Test, 99.8 percentile in JEE Mains, Top 10 percentile in IIT-JEE
- Secured Gold Medalist in NSO (National Science Olympiad '17), Zonal Rank 3 and National Rank 14.
- Listed in Roll of Honors 2017 in High School for securing Top grades (94%) in CBSE.

EXTRA- CIRCULLAR

- Member of Citi Toastmasters: Given Orientation Speeches for 30+ New hires, conducted events and other social activities.
- **Citi APAC Buddy Program:** Mentoring and guided around 10 new campus grad students in the onboarding and training process to Citi. Mentored 4 Campus Graduates as part of the program.
- Elected Department Representative, Student Council Member, CPC Head, and MIS Student Representative 2019-2021
 Managed all academic-related activities, including coursework planning, project activities, internship activities, etc.
 Coordinated between department/College authorities and the rest of the class for all monitoring formalities, scheduling exams, addressing issues, and other administrative works.
- Co-Head, IGNITE Social Club 2017

Trained and taught underprivileged students for competitive college exams.

Led and managed a team of 30 on technical activities like teaching strategy, resource management, etc., which helped 10 students qualify and get admission to top universities; the later initiative was converted into State Government Project.

- FEST & Other Activities Position of Responsibility:
 - **Head of Events'19,'20 Tech Symposium:** Led a team of 30 to organize the events & workshops to manage footfall of 500. **Organizing Committee of NITTFEST'18, FESTEMBER '18**: Managed Events and participants from a general crowd of 500+, and lead all organizing activities.
- Campus Placement Coursework CPC Team: Software Section Head: Head of CPC Program in University to supervise and Train and mentor junior students for placements and other job opportunities.
- Sports: Part of Citi-Cricket Team. Citi Badminton Team, Citi- Pookolam Competition winner (Site level)
 Vice-Captain at the College Cricket Team & Part of the College Football Team.
 Part of High School Athletic Team Won Interschool Competition. District Cricket Player U-16.

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION